<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Good nevves from France. Containing the insolent demands of the Iesuites. Being against 1. The Kings authoritie. 2. The ordinary iustice of his Maiestie. 3. The dignitie and power of the cardinalls, archbishops, and bishops of other orders &amp; professions. 4. The young scholars vnder them. 5. The good and well-fare of the townes and cities which receiue them. 6. The perfection of sciences. 7. The antiquity &amp; co[m]mandements of the Church. 8. The resolution of the clergie of France, and the letters patents of the Kings; and against the sentences of allowance and registring thereof, which they themselues haue pursued. Together with the decree or finall iudgement of the Kings Privie Councell giuen the 27. day of September 1624. in the ioynt defence of the vniversities of France. And against the Iesuites ... / Translated according to the French copie..</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01159</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11274</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120957</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856148</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856148</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21674</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01159)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21674)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1097:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Good nevves from France. Containing the insolent demands of the Iesuites. Being against 1. The Kings authoritie. 2. The ordinary iustice of his Maiestie. 3. The dignitie and power of the cardinalls, archbishops, and bishops of other orders &amp; professions. 4. The young scholars vnder them. 5. The good and well-fare of the townes and cities which receiue them. 6. The perfection of sciences. 7. The antiquity &amp; co[m]mandements of the Church. 8. The resolution of the clergie of France, and the letters patents of the Kings; and against the sentences of allowance and registring thereof, which they themselues haue pursued. Together with the decree or finall iudgement of the Kings Privie Councell giuen the 27. day of September 1624. in the ioynt defence of the vniversities of France. And against the Iesuites ... / Translated according to the French copie..</title>
                  <author>France. Conseil privé. Arrest du Conseil privé du Roy, donné le 27. de Sept. 1624. pour les Universitéz de France, jointes en cause, contre les Jésuites. English. Selections.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 25, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I[ohn] D[awson] for Iohn Bellamie, and are to be sold at his shop, at the three golden Lyons, neare the Royall Exchange.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>French original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The words "1. The Kings authoritie. .. themselues haue pursued." are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Includes a translation of extracts from: Arrest du Conseil privé du Roy, donné le 27. de Sept. 1624. pour les Universitéz de France, jointes en cause, contre les Jésuites.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesuits --  France --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Universities and colleges --  France --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21674:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21674:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GOOD NEVVES FROM FRANCE.</p>
            <p>Containing the Inſolent Demands of the IESVITES.</p>
            <p>Being againſt
<list>
                  <item>1. The KINGS Authoritie.</item>
                  <item>2. The ordinary Iuſtice of his Maieſtie.</item>
                  <item>3. The dignitie and power of the Cardinalls, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, and Biſhops of other orders &amp; profeſſions.</item>
                  <item>4. The young Scholars vnder them.</item>
                  <item>5. The good and well-fare of the Townes and Cities which receiue them.</item>
                  <item>6. The perfection of Sciences.</item>
                  <item>7. The Antiquity &amp; Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements of the Church.</item>
                  <item>8. The Reſolution of the Clergie of <hi>France,</hi> and the Letters Patents of the Kings; and againſt the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of Allowance and Regiſtring thereof, which they themſelues haue purſued.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>TOGETHER WITH</hi> The Decree or Finall Iudgement of the Kings <hi>Privie Councell giuen the</hi> 27. <hi>day of September</hi> 1624. <hi>In the Ioynt defence of the Vniverſities of</hi> France. <hi>And againſt the</hi> Ieſuites <hi>(in reſpect of their Inſolent demands) whereby they are forbidden to take vpon them the name, title, or qualitie of an Vniverſitie, or to giue Degrees in any facultie or nomination to any</hi> BENEFICES.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated according to the <hi>French</hi> Copie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bellamie,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the three golden Lyons, neare the <hi>Royall Exchange.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:21674:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21674:2"/>
            <head>Good Newes from FRANCE. <hi>CONTAINING</hi> CERTAINE REASONS, Vpon which is grounded the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree or Sentence from the Kings Councell againſt the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> demanding the abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Decree of the Parliament at <hi>Tholouſe.</hi> By which they were commanded, that they ſhould not take vpon them the name, title, or qualitie <hi>of an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie; and that they ſhould not giue any degree in any facultie, nor any nomination to any Benefices.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Vniverſities haue alwayes had ſuch a favour of our KINGS, that they haue beene received when they did demand Iuſtice of their Maieſties, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in their own particular cauſes, but alſo in cauſes which did concerne the publick eſtate of the Kingdome. The Hiſtories and publick Acts do plainly ſhew it, and alſo it may ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly appeare by the Records of the Parliament at <hi>Paris,</hi> that our King <hi>Charles</hi> the 7. when he would reſtore and confirme the rights and fundamentall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21674:3"/>lawes of his Kingdome. And having to this end aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled many great Lords to this Councell, there were heard as well their Atturney Generall, as alſo the Vniverſitie at <hi>Paris,</hi> and vpon that which they did repreſent were made many good Ordinances, to which his Maieſtie did ſware, and cauſed all his Officers and Councell to ſware to them inviolably. It is manifeſt to all the world, that our King is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior to his Aunceſtors in doing Iuſtice to his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, without acceptation of perſons, after GODS Ordinance, by whoſe grace he doth raigne, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to conſerue his royall authoritie, with cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to maintaine his State in all the Bodies whereof it is compoſed againſt all Interpriſes. Therfore haue the Vniverſities being preſt by an extreame neceſſity for to defend themſelues againſt the aſſault, yea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt oppreſſion, which the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> not being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented yet with the diſſolutions and ruines which they haue brought vpon them heretofore, doe now take in hand to bring vpon them, in attributing to themſelues their title and their rights (their title in making ſo many Vniverſities as they haue Colledges of their Societie, their rights in making the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and giving the degrees to the Schollers, yea to them which the Doctors of the Vniverſitie hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, as if they were their ſuperiors.) The ſame V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſitie doe hope that it will not be vnpleaſing to the King, that the Deputies ſhould defend them. And in defending themſelues in the preſence of his Maieſtie, and of the Lords of his Councell, they doe not vphold onely the Decree given to their profit by one of the moſt honorable Parliaments of his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21674:3"/>Kingdome (that is to ſay) the Parliament at <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe,</hi> of which the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> dare demand the Abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo abuſing the favour that his Maieſtie hath done to them in taking one of them for his Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor. A moſt ſingular favour, which till this preſent they haue not received of any of our holy Fathers, nor of the Kings of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alſo doe ſhew and proue by authentick Acts, yea by the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> owne writings, that the demand which they doe make now, and the proiects which they haue to attribute to every one of their Colled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the title and rights of an Vniverſitie, are contrary and preiudiciall to the Kings authoritie, to the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Iuſtice of his Maieſtie, to the dignitie and power of the Cardinals, Archbiſhops, and Biſhops of other orders and profeſſions, to the yong Schollers vnder them, and to the good of the Townes which doe receiue them, to the perfection of Sciences and Antiquitie, &amp; to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements of the Church, and to the reſolution of the Clergie of <hi>France</hi> in the aſſembly at <hi>Poiſſy,</hi> in the yeare 1561. to the Letters Patents which they haue obtained of our Kings, <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Francis</hi> the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth, <hi>Henry</hi> the third, and to thoſe Letters which they haue had for the re-eſtabliſhing of the King <hi>Henry</hi> the Great, of happie memory, and of our King which doth raigne at this preſent. As alſo to the Decrees of the allowance and regiſtring thereof, which they themſelues haue purſued in the Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Kingdome.</p>
            <div n="1" type="argument">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21674:4"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Againſt the Kings authoritie.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe they will by vertue of a Bull which they ſay that they haue obtained from our holy <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the 13. take vpon them power for to chuſe and create Iudges, Conſervators for all kinde of cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes as well Civill as Criminall, and mixt: yea, &amp; thoſe in which they themſelues ſhould be demanders for their rights, lands, and houſes, fruits, rents, and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, and for all other things moueable and vnmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable, ſpirituall and temporall: and that the Iudges which they ſhould haue received, ſhould doe Iuſtice according to the will of the rector of their Vniverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Againſt the Kings Authoritie.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe by vertue of an Inſtitution inferted and related in a Bull which they haue obtained in the yeare 1540. of our holy Father the Pope, they retaine for their Generall, (which ſince their comming till this preſent day hath beene a ſtranger, a <hi>Spanyard,</hi> or one borne vnder the ſubiection of <hi>Spaine</hi>) all kinde of government and ſoveraigne authoritie over the Scholars which are of their Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and over their Colledges, and over all others which are of their Societie, for to obey him alwayes, and to acknowledge him as one who hath the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: and in their Vow they doe promiſe to him as to one which keepeth the place of God, all obedience, not onely for things obligatory, but alſo for all other things, though
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21674:4"/>there ſhould appeare no other thing to them but a ſigne of the Generalls will, without any expreſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement: in doing all things that which ſhould be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded, in perſwading themſelues things to be lawfull, &amp; in renouncing through a blind obedience, all advice and iudgement to the contrary, ſuffering themſelues to be carried and vſed even as a dead corpſe, willing that no particular perſon, directly or indirectly, without the permiſſion and approbation of their Generall, ſhould aske or cauſe to be asked of our holy Father the Pope, nor of any other which is without the Societie, any grace for himſelfe or for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: and that he ſhould beleeue if he did not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his deſire of his Generall, or with his conſent thereto, it is not for him, though it were for diuine ſervice: and on the contrary, if it be fit for him by the conſent of his Generall, which keepes the place of our Saviour Ieſus Chriſt for him, that he ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it. And that which is ſaid of the Colledges, muſt alſo be vnderſtood to be ſaid of the Vniverſities of the Societie in the ſame manner, that if they obtaine that which they demand for this preſent time, one muſt no more ſay for the royall Vniverſitie of <hi>Paris,</hi> but the Vniverſitie of the Societie, and ſo of all other Vniverſities of this Kingdome. And although that he doth communicate his power to other inferiors, which are in the Provinces, Viſitators and Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners, yet alwayes he hath power to approue or to abrogate and make void that which they haue done, and to ordeine in all things that which he thinketh good. And alwayes they muſt obey him and honor him as one that is the Vicar of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="argument">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:21674:5"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Againſt the Kings authoritie.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe they haue a generall Agent which gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth advice to the Generall, as well of perſons as of things, as it pleaſeth them. And their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall hath foure Aſſiſtants, one for the buſineſſe of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> another for <hi>Italy,</hi> and <hi>Sicilie,</hi> the other for <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Portugall,</hi> and the other, of the <hi>Indies.</hi> And generally for to doe all things he hath a Generall Atturney of the Societie, and he hath eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yeare a Catalogue ſent vnto him of all the Houſes and Colledges of the Societies, and another of all the Perſons which are in every Province. They will alſo that there be in their pretended Vniverſities, a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary of the Societie, which keepeth a Booke, in which are written all the names of them which come to their Colledges, and which of them doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue promiſe to obey the Rector, and to obſerue the Conſtitution. And if there are ſome which doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to giue their names, and ſo doe regiſter and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>role themſelues, that he ſhould repreſent and ſhew them, becauſe they ſhould take more particular care to the Schollers, whoſe names are written in the Booke of the Vniverſitie, and to ſpeake it plainely and without diſſembling, what can one ſay more, as to enrole, ſeduce, and retaine men for a ſtranger, as alwayes till this day the Generall of the ſaid Societie hath beene. And this cannot be done in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome without contrarietie, and infinite preiudice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Kings authoritie. No man can ſerue two ſeverall Lords, nor can as a ſubiect and vaſſall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the one and the other for his Lord. Our
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21674:5"/>King cannot be acknowledged &amp; ſerved by a Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, vpon the conditions here related, more then our holy Father the Pope can be in qualitie of a Vicar of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, as the Vniverſities with the Catholick, Apoſtolick, and Romane Church do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him for; and as a Generall that keepeth Gods place, and is our Lord Ieſus Chriſts Vicar. But if they for to cloak this, ſay like as they are wont to doe, that they doe vow a particular obedience to his <hi>Holines,</hi> we anſwer, that they doe ſuppreſſe it with that is written in their Conſtitutions, that it is onely for the Miſſions, and then they attribute to their Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall the full direction and power thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Againſt his Maieſties ordinary Iuſtice.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe that no bodie of their Colledges and Houſes, whether he be of thoſe which haue made their vowes, or of their helpers, or of their Scholars, muſt ſuffer himſelfe to be examined for ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and much leſſe for criminall cauſes, without the leaue of their ſuperior, and that their ſuperior muſt giue no leaue, if it be not in cauſes that concerne the Catholike Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Against the dignitie and power of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalls, Archbiſhops, and Biſhops.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe they take away from them the power and authoritie of iudging, otherwiſe then is written in the Bull, which they ſay they haue gotten for to chuſe Iudges, Conſervators in all civill and crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall cauſes, and they doe conſtraine them to iudge and decree according to their Inſtitutes and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21674:6"/>by vertue of a Bull which they had from our holy Father the Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> XIII. in the yeare 1584 which beareth the greateſt excommunication, and a penaltie of diſabilitie to any Offices and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices fecular and regular of all Orders, and that as ſoone as the deed ſhall be done, without any other declaration againſt all perſons of whatſoever condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and preeminence they be, which ſhall withſtand and gaineſay directly and indirectly the Inſtitutes and Conſtitutions of this Societie, or any of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, vnder colour of diſputation, and ſeeking of the truth. As alſo they doe attribute by vertue of their Inſtitutes, Bulls, and Conſtitutions to their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall the Government of all the Vniverſities which they haue. Which doth exclude and depriue the Cardinalls, Archbiſhops, and Biſhops, of the right and poſſeſſion that they haue as Governors and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors of the Vniverſities, which doth exempt many Clerkes of their Iuriſdiction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Againſt the Rules and Profeſsions of other Orders.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe that they in reſpect of thoſe which haue a portion with them that they take the beſt Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices for to ioyne them to their Colledges, as it is manifeſt; and in reſpect of others, they doe take vpon them all the Faculties, Conceſſions, exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Indulgences, remiſſion of ſinnes, and grace as well ſpirituall as temporall, granted, &amp; yet to be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, which haue and ſhall haue in time to come all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Orders of beggars, Prieſts and Nunnes for to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy by them for all and in the whole ſo as they themſelues, yea with as much right, and they will
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21674:6"/>that all thoſe which doe ſtudie in their Colledges, or pretended Vniverſities, doe promiſe that they will obey them, and obſerue all their Conſtitutions, for ſo much that if any Prieſts doe ſtudie and take their degree and promotion, as there doe many in the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſitie at <hi>Paris,</hi> and other Vniverſities, they ſhould be bound againſt the rules of their Orders and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, to promiſe obedience to no other then their Superiors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Against the young Scholars, which are vnder them.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe the profeſſed Societie muſt take no care to teach in their Colledges perfection of liuing, &amp; Letters worthy to a Chriſtian, but onely thoſe which are eſteemed to haue the Talent, for they ſhall be as a Nurſe-gardian to the profeſſed Societie, &amp; to his helpers, and they know that if with the Colled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the Vniverſities were alſo committed to the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, keeping in proceeding, the manner of which is ſpoken in the fourth part, they helpe to the ſame end, adding thereunto theſe ſpeeches; <hi>For the greater good of God, and the generall good of the Societie,</hi> which know certainly, that they doe not eſtabliſh their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Vniverſities, but onely for their particular intereſt and profit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Againſt the Wealth of the Cities which doe receiue them.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe they giue power to themſelues for to leaue and abandon the Colledges and Houſes which they haue eſtabliſhed, and they ſay that if
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21674:7"/>it doth appeare by proofe that the Societie is more hindred then helped, and their Generall doth finde no remedie for it, that it then is lawfull to conſider in the firſt generall Congregation, whether ſuch an Houſe, Colledge, or Vniverſitie ought to be aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned or kept, with ſuch a charge, and in abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it, they will diſpoſe of it, and of all the revenues given vnto them, if there be not made an expreſſe reſervation to the contrary by them which haue bin the builders of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Againſt the perfection of Sciences.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe they doe reduce their pretended Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities vnto three faculties: One for the Tongues, another for the Arts, and the third for Theologie; and they will not that there ſhould be any Treatiſe of Phyſicke, nor of the lawes (though it be manifeſt that they are more neceſſary for man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde) or at leaſt, that the Societie ſhould not be charged with it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="argument">
               <head>
                  <hi>10.</hi> Againſt Antiquitie and the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Church.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe that their Scholars, and eſpecially thoſe which dwell in their Colledges, doe more then they heare and vnderſtand the great Maſſe ſaid by a Deacon and Subdeacon, for they doe not ſay it in their Churches, as it is knowne to every one, and they haue no Quiere, and they doe derogate the generall Councells.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="argument">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21674:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>11.</hi> Against the reſolution of the Clergie of <hi>France</hi> that was aſſembled at <hi>Poiſy,</hi> in the yeare <hi>1501.</hi> Against the Letters patents of our King and against the ſentences of allowance and registring thereof, which they themſelues haue purſued.</head>
               <p>BEcauſe they doe take vpon them the title, name and rights of the Vniuerſitie. The title and name in giuing the qualitie of an Vniuerſity to euery one of their Colledges for to make ſo many Vniuerſities as they haue Colledges. The rights in making the Promotions and in giuing the degrees to the Scholars, yea to them to whom the Doctors of the Vniuerſities haue refuſed it, if it be that their examiners do find them capable, as if they were their ſuperiors. For by the reſolution of the Clergie here dated, and by the Letters patents of our Kings here mentioned, and by the ſentence of allowance and regiſtring thereof, which they themſelues haue pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued in the Courts of Parliament of this kingdome, it is expreſſely forbidden that they ſhould doe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing either ſpirituall or temporall in preiudice of of the Vniuerſities: and they can doe no greater pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21674:8"/>to the Vniuerſities then to make Vniuerſities of their Colledges, and to eſtabliſh them and giue them the titles and rights of Vniuerſities like to them of <hi>Paris</hi> and others of this Kingdome.</p>
               <p>The Parties were heard on Friday laſt, the 28. of <hi>September</hi> 1624. in the Hall where the Councell was kept at S. <hi>Germain</hi> in <hi>Lay,</hi> where was a great multitude of people, and the Ieſuties demandants were thruſt from their Letters of abrogation, and it was ordained that the decree or ſentence at <hi>Tholouſe</hi> ſhould ſtand in full force and power.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="decree">
            <pb facs="tcp:21674:8"/>
            <head>Good Newes from FRANCE. <hi>CONTAINING</hi> A DECREE or FINALL Iudgement from the Kings privie Councell, given the 27 day of <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1624. for the Vniverſities of FRANCE, ioyntly againſt the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> demanding the abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Decree of the Parliament of <hi>Tholouſe.</hi> By which they were forbidden to take vpon them the name, title, and qualitie of an Vniverſitie, <hi>and to giue Degrees in any facultie, or Nomination to any</hi> Benefices.</head>
            <head type="sub">An extract out of the Regiſters of the KINGS <hi>Privie Councell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Etweene the ſocietie of the Vniuerſitie of the towne of <hi>Tournon,</hi> being of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> demandant in a requeſt and a decree from the Councell giuen vpon the ſame, on the 15. of <hi>Decem.</hi> 1623. &amp; defendant on the one part: And the ſocietie of the Vniuerſities of <hi>Tholouſe, Valence Cahors</hi> defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants; and the ſaid ſocietie of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> demandant in a requeſt of the 19. <hi>Iuly</hi> laſt paſt, on the other part, without which the qualities may not hinder or preiudice them. And alſo the Rector, Deans, At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneys and Deputies of the Vniuerſity of <hi>Paris;</hi> the Rector, Doctors and regents of the Vniuerſity of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21674:9"/>
               <hi>Bourdeaux;</hi> the Rector, Doctors, and deputies of the Vniuerſity of <hi>Reims,</hi> the Rector, Dean, and deputies of the Vniuerſity of <hi>Portiers;</hi> the Rector, Deans, and deputies of the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Caen;</hi> the Rector Deans, and Doctors of the Vniuerſities of <hi>Bourges, Orleans, Anger,</hi> and <hi>Aix,</hi> coming all on the other part.</p>
            <p>The which petition and the decree vpon the ſame dated the 15. of <hi>December</hi> 1623. being ſeene by the King in his Councell. In reſpect of the things therein contained, it pleaſed his Maieſtie to abrogate and make voyde the decree from the Parliament of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> giuen againſt the demandant to the profit of the ſaid Vniuerſities of <hi>Tholouſe, Vallence,</hi> &amp; <hi>Cahors,</hi> the 4. of <hi>Iuly</hi> of the ſaid year: &amp; ſo doing to ordaine, that the decree of the rule of the Letters patents agreed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſaid Vniuerſitie of <hi>Tournon,</hi> in the month of <hi>December</hi> 1622. ſhould be executed according to the force and tenor thereof, and that the ſaid Vniuerſitie ſhould be maintained and kept in the poſſeſſion and enioying the Priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, rights, and powers, to them agreed by the ſame: the Bulls of our holy Father the Pope <hi>Iulies</hi> Letters patents of the ratifying thereof, and decrees of the regiſtring, notwithſtanding the oppoſitions of the ſaid Vniuerſities of <hi>Tholouſe, Vallence,</hi> and <hi>Cahors,</hi> to defend the ſaid ſocietie of the ſaid Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, not to helpe themſelues with the ſaid decree of of the 13. of <hi>Iuly,</hi> nor vnder colour of the ſame to trouble nor hinder the Rector, regents, and ſcholars, &amp; deputies of the ſaid Vniuerſity of <hi>Tournon</hi> directly, nor indirectly in the enioying of the liberties, facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and powers, which to them haue beene giuen,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21674:9"/>granted, confirmed, &amp; augmented vpon penaltie of one thouſand pounds coſts dammages and intereſts: by which decree was ordayned that the ſocietie of the ſaid Vniuerſities of <hi>Tholouſe, Vallence,</hi> and <hi>Cahors</hi> ſhould be cald for, and in the meanetime that the ſaid Rector and regents of the ſayd Vniuerſities of <hi>Tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non</hi> ſhould enioy the ſame Priuiledges, Authorities, Preeminences, and liberty which they did enioy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſaid Letters of the month of <hi>December</hi> 1622. A Commiſſion vpon the ſaid decree on the ſaid day. Acts of aſſignements of the 5.9. and 13. of <hi>Ianu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie</hi> laſt paſt. A copy of Bulls obtained by the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall of <hi>Tournon</hi> deceaſed, of Pope <hi>Iulie</hi> 3. being creator of the ſaid Vniuerſitie of <hi>Tournon,</hi> there to make generall ſtudyes in Latine, Greek, Hebrew, Chaldean tongues, and morall, and naturall Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie; euen as the other Vniuerſities; giuen in <hi>Rome,</hi> in the yeare 1552. the 3. day of <hi>May.</hi> For the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of which, there are copies of the Letters of King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, of the 9. of <hi>Nouember,</hi> of the ſame yeare being dated to the ſaid Parliament of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> and to the Seneſchall of <hi>Beaucaire</hi> &amp; <hi>Niſmes</hi> for the proclaiming and regiſtring of the ſaid Bulls. Alſo the Act of the proclaiming and regiſtring in the ſaid Parliament of <hi>Tholouſe</hi> the 11. of <hi>Aprill</hi> 1553. And in the regiſtry of the Archbiſhop extracted out of the regiſters of the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning certaine concluſions and demands made by the Kings ſeruants in the ſaid Parliament of the 26. <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1552. A copie of a contract of giſt and legacie made foreuer by the ſaid Sir <hi>de Tournon</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21674:10"/>the ſaid Fathers the Ieſuits of the Colledge which he had cauſed to be builded in the ſaid towne of <hi>Tournon,</hi> with the appurtenances, dependancies and reuenue at the charge contained in the clauſes and conditions, as be declared by the ſayd contract paſſed before <hi>Gilles Meſnager</hi> and <hi>Malthurin Porcher</hi> Notaries publike in the court of Iuſtice at <hi>Orleans</hi> the 6. <hi>Ianuary</hi> 1560. accepted by <hi>Don Iohn Baptiſt Violle</hi> a Prieſt &amp; Atturny generall of the Ioſuites. And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer is put downe the copie of the Procuration of the generall of the ſaid Fathers the Ieſuites, for to accept the ſaid gift and legacie of the 28. of <hi>October,</hi> of the ſame yeare: alſo the acte from the aſſembly that the Prieſts of the Abby of <hi>Chaiſe-Dieu</hi> being vnited to the ſaid Colledge, had; which did approue and authorize the ſaid contract of the 24. of <hi>February</hi> in the ſame yeare; extracted out of the regiſter of the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> concerning the Kings and the Queenes (his mothers) Letters for the verifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the afore going Letters patents, to the allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and approbation of the Bulls, priviledges, and inſtitutions of the ſaid Fathers to the Ieſuites in the ſaid yeare 1560. A ſuite in Law of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Meſnill</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, Aduocate in the cauſe of the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Paris,</hi> and of the Fathers the Ieſuites, followes the Counſell and reſolution of the aſſembly of the Clergy of <hi>France</hi> kept at <hi>Poiſsy,</hi> in the yeare 1561. A copy of the act of the aſſembly kept by the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church at <hi>Poiſſy</hi> aforeſaid the 15. of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1561. A copy of the decree from the ſayd Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament at <hi>Paris</hi> of the 13. of <hi>February</hi> in the ſaid
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21674:10"/>yeare 1561. By which is ordained that the ſaid Act made in the aſſembly at <hi>Poiſſy,</hi> ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred vnder the conditions therein conteined. A copy of the Letters Patents of the King <hi>Charles</hi> the ninth, giuen in the moneth of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1561. for the conformation and allowance of the ſaid gift and tranſport. A copy of the Decree of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> of the foureteenth day of <hi>Febru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arie</hi> in the ſaid yeare 1561. for the Proclayming and regiſtring of the ſaid Letters of gift, vpon the charges and conditions as are mentioned in the Act of the Aſſembly kept at <hi>Poiſſy,</hi> the fifteenth day of <hi>September</hi> in the ſaid yeare. A reliefe of King <hi>Henry</hi> the third, of the thirteenth day of <hi>Aprill,</hi> 1584. to the Parliaments of <hi>Paris, Roan, Bourdeaux, Dauphine, Province</hi> and <hi>Borgongne,</hi> for to verifie and regiſter the ſayd Bulls of the ſaid Vniuerſitie at <hi>Tournon,</hi> and of the ratification which is Regiſtred at <hi>Paris, Grenoble,</hi> and <hi>Province</hi> the ninth day of <hi>Iune,</hi> the ninth day of <hi>Nouember,</hi> and the nineteenth day of <hi>December,</hi> in the ſaid yeare, 1584. A Decree of the court of Parliament at <hi>Aix</hi> for the verification of the ſaid Bulls and Letters the nineteenth day of <hi>December,</hi> 1584. A decree of the Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>Paris</hi> of the nineteenth day of <hi>Iune</hi> 1584. for the execution of the ſaid Letters Patents of the thirteenth day of <hi>Aprill</hi> aforeſaid, in the ſame yeare; by which was ordayned that the ſaid Letters and Bulls ſhould be regiſtred, without which they may hinder or preiudice the freedome of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21674:11"/>
               <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, and without which the Patentees may take vpon them no other qualitie then of Scholars of the Colledge at <hi>Tournon,</hi> A Copie of a Petition extracted out of the Records of of the Vniuerſitie at <hi>Paris,</hi> the ſeuenteenth day of this preſent moneth of <hi>September.</hi> An o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Copy of a Declaration made by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the Ieſuites to the ſaid Vniuerſitie, and extracted out of the ſayd Records on the ſame day. A Copy of a Petition preſented to the Parliament at <hi>Paris,</hi> by the Prieſts and Scholars of the Societie and companie of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> of the Colledge at <hi>Clermont,</hi> vpon the reception to the Aſſemblie at <hi>Poiſſy,</hi> and the Concluſions of the Cheefe Atturney of the ſayd Parliament: extracted alſo out of the ſayd Records on the ſayd day. A printed Copy of the Edict vpon the reeſtabliſhing of the Fathers, the Ieſuites giuen at <hi>Roan</hi> in the moneth of <hi>September,</hi> 1603. Letters in the forme of a Comminaltie of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Great deceaſed in the moneth of <hi>October,</hi> 1604. By the which hee had allowed the ſayd foundation; and for ſo much as it ſhould be neceſſarie, confirmed the ſaid Priuiledges and rights.</p>
            <p>Other Letters in the forme of a Comminaltie of the moneth of December 1622. bearing ſuch a like Confirmation, vnderneath which is the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring of the Parliament at <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> of the ninth of Ianuary 1623. A Decree of the ſaid Parliament of the ninth of March of the ſaid yeare 1623. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21674:11"/>the ſaid Demandants ſhould enioy the effect of the ſaid Letters. And a Copie of an Act from the Aſſembly kept in the great Hall of the Colledge and Vniverſitie at <hi>Aix,</hi> on the twentie-fifth day of Aprill of the ſaid yeare 1623. by thoſe of the ſaid Colledge and Vniverſitie. A Copie of the Letters which the ſaid Defendants haue obtained in the Chauncery at <hi>Tholouſe</hi> the twelfth of Aprill 1624. for being received as Oppoſants againſt the Decree of the aboue-ſaid Regiſtring. An exploit of an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignement of the fourth of May 1624. An Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of a Preſentation done in the ſaid Aſſigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on the ſeaventeenth day following. A De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the ſaid Parliament at <hi>Tholouſe</hi> the thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth day of Iuly, in the ſaid yeare 1623. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Societie of the ſaid Vniverſities at <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe, Vallence,</hi> and <hi>Cahors,</hi> having obtained the Kings Letters againſt the ſaid Societie of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> at <hi>Tournon.</hi> By the which allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid Letters, the ſaid Obtainers were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived as Oppoſants to the Examination of the ſaid Decree of the Regiſtring; and without having any regard therevnto, the ſaid Fathers the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> at <hi>Tournon</hi> were forbidden that they ſhould take vpon them any name, title, or qualitie of an Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie, neither to giue any Catholickes of Studie, nor any Degrees in any Facultie, nor any nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Benefices, vpon penaltie of diſſolution, and other ſentences: nevertheleſſe that all Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall Degrees and Nominations, which are given by them by authoritie of the ſame Decree of the Regiſtring, ſhould be of no value. And alſo they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21674:12"/>which might haue obtained them, are forbidden not to vſe the ſame vpon penaltie of the fiue hundred pounds, without preiudice of the ſaid Decree of the Regiſtring concerning the vnion of the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits there onely mentioned. A Decree of the ſaid Parliament at <hi>Tholouſe</hi> of the eleventh of the ſaid moneth of Iuly, ſaying, That notwithſtanding the things aboue-ſaid and alledged by <hi>Brun,</hi> Attour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of the Societie of the Colledge of the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> at <hi>Tournon</hi> hee ſhould poſſeſſe, and the parties ſhould appeare preciſely on Thurſday next. An Act of an Atteſtation of the twentie-fourth of May 1624. paſſed before the Seneſchall at <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> that Maſter <hi>Iohn de Brun,</hi> Atturney in the Court, was Atturney of the ſaid Fathers the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> which are of the Iuriſdiction of the Parliament at <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> and in the ſaid qualitie did all their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, as well in demanding as defending. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Decree from the Parliament vpon a Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the chiefe Atturney of the eleventh of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt 1623. By which all Rectors, Principalls, and Over-ſeers of the Colledges, and of the Iuriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as well of the ſaid Fathers the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> as others, were forbidden to giue any Teſtimonialls of the Studie in Parchment, with a ſeale, nor with a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face. A quire of writing Paper Printed, containing the declarations of the twenty one of Ianuary 154 and of the twenty-third of Iune 1594. And Letters Patents of the moneth of December 1610. of the priviledges granted by the King to the ſaid Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities at <hi>Paris.</hi> And the Decrees in conſequence given to the privie Councell the ſeaventeenth of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21674:12"/>December 1604. and the nineteenth of Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 1612. A Petition of an Intervention of the ſaid Rector, Deanes, Atturneyes, and Deputies of the ſaid Vniverſitie at <hi>Paris,</hi> the parties interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelues were received the ſeaventeenth of Iune laſt paſt. A ſignification of the twentieth of the ſaid Moneth. Another Petition of Intervention of the Rector, Doctor, and Regent of the Vniverſitie at <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> the parties interpoſing themſelues were received, and there was an Act given vnto them of that they had imployed for the Interven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſaid Petition, and of that which had beene written and produced by the ſaid Vniverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie at <hi>Paris;</hi> as alſo thoſe at <hi>Tholouſe, Valence,</hi> and <hi>Cahors,</hi> the twentith of this preſent moneth of September. A ſignification of the ſaid day. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Petition of Intervention from the Rector, Doctors, and Deputies of the Vniverſitie at <hi>Reims,</hi> the parties interpoſing themſelues, were received the twentie-fifth of the ſaid moneth of September. A ſignification of the ſame day. Another Petition of Intervention from the Rector, Deanes, and Deputies of the Vniverſitie at <hi>Poictiers;</hi> the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties interpoſing were receiued in the moneth of Iune laſt paſt. An Act of a declaration, that for all their Productions and Intervention, they did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy the ſaid Petition, and all that which had beene written and produced by the Vniverſitie at <hi>Paris.</hi> A ſignification of the moneth of September then next following. Another Petition of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention from the Rector, Deanes, and Deputies of the Vniverſitie of <hi>Caen;</hi> the parties interpoſing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21674:13"/>themſelues were received the twenty-two of the ſaid moneth of Iune. An Act of a declaration that he would imploy the ſaid Petition for their Producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and all that which had beene produced and written by the Vniverſitie at <hi>Paris.</hi> A ſignification of the twenty-third of September. A Petition of Intervention from the Rectors, Deanes, and Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the Vniverſities at <hi>Bourges,</hi> and <hi>Orleance;</hi> the parties interpoſing themſelues were received the twentieth of September, and an Act of their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. A ſignification of the ſaid day. Petitions of Intervention from the Vniverſitie at <hi>Aix,</hi> and <hi>Angers.</hi> A Petition of the Chancellor, Rector, and Doctors of the Vniverſitie of <hi>Cahors,</hi> that they did imploy for their Production that which had beene written and produced by the ſaid Rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and Doctors of the Vniverſitie at <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> whereof they haud had an Act the twelfth of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt laſt paſt. A ſignification of the ſaid day: a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition of the Societie at <hi>Tholouſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A decree vpon the ſame that the Parties may be heard throughly of the ſame day the ninteenth day of <hi>Iuly</hi> laſt paſt. A direction in conſequence of the fifteenth day of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> A direction betweene the ſaid parties, of the two and twentieth day of <hi>Aprill</hi> laſt paſt, there to communicate, write and produce writings and productions, and all that which hath bin produced before my Lord of the ludgement Court, Councellour to the King in his Priuie Councell, and ordinarie Maſter of the Petitions, of this Hall, as Commiſſioner hereto appointed, and to hear his report. And after that Maſter <hi>Iohn
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21674:13"/>Aubert</hi> Rector of the ſayd Vniuerſitie at <hi>Paris,</hi> hath beene heard for all the Vniuerſities at <hi>France,</hi> being. The King and his Councell at the ſame Inſtance of abrogation hath acquited, and doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite the ſaid Parties out of fuite; Prouided that the Demanders may prouide themſelues by a ciuill Petition againſt the ſaid Decree in the ſaid Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament at <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> and there beſides vpon the finall concluſion of the ſayd Interpoſers, his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie doth ordaine that they ſhould prouide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſo as they ſhould thinke it fit, and without coſt. Done in the Kings priuie Councell kept at S. <hi>Germaine en Laye</hi> the ſeuen and twentith day of <hi>September</hi> 1624. And this vnderneath conferd.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed. De Choiſy.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Evvis by the Grace of God, King of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Nauarre,</hi> to Our cheefe Vſher and Sargieant, herevnto requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſend greeting. We doe charge &amp; command you by theſe preſents, that the Decree of our Councell hereto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21674:14"/>vnder Our Counter-ſeale giuen to day betweene the Societie of the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of the Towne of <hi>Tournon,</hi> of the Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> Demandant and Defendant on the one part, and the Agent of the Vniuerſitie at <hi>Tholouſe, Vallence</hi> and <hi>Cahors,</hi> Defendants; and the ſaid Agent of <hi>Tholouſe,</hi> Demandant on the other part; And alſo the Rectors, Deanes, Atturnyes, Doctors, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, and Deputies of the Vniuerſities at <hi>Paris, Bourdeaux, Reimes, Poictiers, Caen, Bourges, Orleans, Angers</hi> and <hi>Aix,</hi> depoſing themſelues on the other part: That you doe ſignifie vnto the ſaid Agent of the Societie of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and all other to whom it ſhall apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that they doe not pretend any cauſe of Ignorance, but that they do obey here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto: Commanding them in Our name, not to doe any thing againſt it, but to doe this and all other acts and exploits required, and neceſſarie for the execution of Our ſaid Decree, vpon the requeſt of the ſaid Doctor, Deane, Atturney, and Deputie of the ſaid Vniuerſitie at <hi>Paris,</hi> We doe charge you, without demanding
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21674:14"/>any leaue. Hereof faile you not, for ſo is Our pleaſure. Giuen at S. <hi>Germain en Lay,</hi> the 27. of <hi>September, Anno Dom.</hi> 1624. and of Our Raigne the 15.</p>
            <p>Vnderneath is written by the King and his Councell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Signed De Choiſy.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:21674:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21674:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A GAGGE FOR THE POPE, AND THE IESVITS: <hi>OR</hi> THE ARRAIGNEMENT, AND EXECVTION OF ANTICHRIST.</p>
            <p>Shevving plainely, that Antichriſt ſhall be diſcouered, and puniſhed in this VVorld: <hi>to the amaſement of all obſtinate</hi> PAPISTS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Edward Blackmore,</hi> and are to be ſould at his Shop, at the Great South-dore of <hi>Paules.</hi> 1624.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
